Guide to the Woodrow Wilson Miscellaneous Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Woodrow Wilson miscellaneous collection
1877-1958
1877-1925
MS 716
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.25
(9 boxes, 3 folios)
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, photographs, speeches and messages, writings, memorabilia, and writings about Woodrow Wilson. The correspondence is primarily between Wilson and Winthrop More Daniels, (1878-) Princeton University faculty member 1892-1911, and Interstate Commerce Commission, 1914-1923.
Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Winthrop M. Daniels, 1940.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Woodrow Wilson Miscellaneous Collection consists of correspondence, printed matter, photographs, film and memorabilia related to Woodrow Wilson's academic and political career.
The correspondence is primarily between Winthrop M. Daniels and Woodrow Wilson. Daniels served on the Princeton faculty between 1892 and 1911, and on the Interstate Commerce Commission between 1914 and 1923. The letters written prior to 1911 deal primarily with concerns such as faculty appointments, the Graduate College, and other university and educational matters. The majority of the later correspondence deals with issues such as regulation of the railroads and public utilities. There are also letters and copies of letters between Wilson and persons other than Daniels and between Daniels and persons other than Wilson.
The printed matter consists of speeches and messages by Wilson, books and articles by Wilson, and writings about Wilson. The boks and articles include an autographed copy of Constitutional Government and a broken series of Princeton University annual reports. The writnigs about Wilson include articles, correspondence, and memorabilia related to the Wilson centennial in 1956.
The remaining items consist of photographs and portraits of Wilson, newspaper clippings and a C.B.S. Film about him, memorabilia from the presidential campaign of 1912, the second draft of the Covenant of the League of Nations, and a memorandum about blockade provisions. The drafts and the memorandum are annotated by Wilson.
Biographical / Historical
A.B., Princeton, 1879, A.M., 1882; grad. in Law, U. of Va., 1881; practiced law in Atlanta, Ga., 1882-1883; Ph.D., Johns Hopkins, 1886; prof. at Bryn Mawr, Wesleyan, Princeton, 1885-1910; pres. of Princeton, 1902-1910; gov. of N.J., 1911-1913; pres. of the United States, 1913-1921; author of many books.
Education; Presidents -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- History -- 1901-1953; United States -- Politics and government; Educators; Public officers; Daniels, Winthrop More, 1867-1944; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Princeton University -- History
- Inventory, 1877-1958
  - Correspondence between Woodrow Wilson and:
    - Baker, Newton D., Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bok, Edward, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brown, William Garrett, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dabney, R. Heath, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Daniels, Winthrop M.
      - 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1895, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      - 1906, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 1909 April-1915 (Box 1, Folder 10-16)
      - 1916 February-1917 August (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - 1917 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 1918 February-October (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
      - 1922 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Davis, Norman H., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Garfield, Harry Augustus, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gregory, Thomas Watt, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Harlem, John M., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Joline, Adrian H. (with copy of speech at Parsons, Kansas, which prompted Wilson's "cocked hat" reference to Bryan.), 1907 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Kechan, William F., 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Miller, George D., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Nansen, Fridtjof, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Palmer, A. Mitchell, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Plunkett, Horace, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Seely, Fred Loring, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence between Winthrop M. Daniels and:
    - Baker, Ray Stannard, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Tumulty, Joseph P., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Whitney, Travis H., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Speeches and messages
    - 1880 March-1895 May (Box 1)
    - 1895 June-1909 November (Box 2)
    - 1910 January-1916 June (Box 3)
    - 1916 September-1919 September, undated (Box 4)
  - Books and articles
    - 1877-1906 (Box 5)
    - 1906-1923 (Box 6)
  - Writings about Wilson (by author)
    - A-W, author unidentified (Box 7)
    - Author unidentified (Box 8)
  - Woodrow Wilson Foundation addresses and Wilson centennial papers
    - Photographs (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter (Box 9)
    - Memorabilia (Box 9)
  - Film (Box 10)
  - Posters of 20th Century-Fox film on Wilson (Box 11)
  - Two certificates announcing the appointment of Winthrop M. Daniels to the Interstate Commerce Commission in 1914 and 1917, respectively, 1914, 1917 (Box 12)